<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<resources>

    <string-array name="deep_step">

        <item>     1 Get comfortable in your prefered meditaon posture.2. Put one palm on your upper chest and the other over your navel.                    3. Breathe in slowly through your nose - noce the stomach moving out.
            The hand on your chest remains sll.               4. Breathe out fully and then a lile bit more. Ensure that the hand on your upper chest is sll.                        5. Pause for 2 seconds.                            6. Allow the air to naturally ?ow in again.
            7.  Imagine your muscles are relaxing with every exhalaon.                  8. Slowly and calmly repeat this cycle a few mes
        </item>
        <item>   1. Get comfortable in your prefered meditaon posture.            2. Close your eyes and focus on your breathing.                    3.Don’t force it, just observe it come in and go out.                           4. When you breathe in, imagine that your lungs are in your stomach, under your navel.
            5. Imagine the feeling of the warm air going all the way down to the stomach.                   6. Follow your breath back up again, from your stomach and out through your nose.                     7. Repeat the exercise.
        </item>
        <item>1. Get comfortable in your prefered meditaon posture.             2. Bring your aenon on your breathing.               3. Don’t force it, just observe it come in and go out.                           4. Now imagine that the air you inhale enters a balloon.
            5. Pick a color for the balloon- let it be a happy color.                   6. Take a deep breath through your nose and imagine the balloons expanding.                      7. Breathe out and imagine the balloon de?ate. Noce how it feels.
            8. Don’t force it. If you are comfortable keep adding balloons as you repeat the exercise
</item>
        <item> 1. Choose a comfortable meditaon posture.                02. Anchor your focus on your breathing.               .Don’t force it, just observe it come in and go out.                   03. On the next breath in, noce how the ribcage slowly expands outwards and then contracts inwards as you exhale.
            04. Connue to breathe and keep observing this movement of the ribcage without trying to alter it in any way.                     05. Now imagine- that every me your ribcage expands it is moving further and further outwards.                         06. When you are comfortable, imagine the ribcage as so and free ?owing.
            07. Visualize it as billowing around the room as if with a life of its own expanding and contracng with your breath.                         08. Connue with the exercise each me expanding the ribcage e?ortlessly.                     09. Don’t force it. Inhale and exhale comfortably.
                       10. When you are ready, return to normal breathing and as you do so let the image of the expanding ribcage fade away.
</item>
        <item>01. Choose a comfortable meditaon posture                02. Anchor your focus on your breathing. Don’t force it, just observe it come in and go out.                      03. Noce the sensaons and become aware of the feelings  you are experiencing                           04. Start with your le foot. Focus your aenon on how it feels
            05. Connue up the body, spending 30 seconds to focus on each part of the body                       06. Allow each part to be as it is ,just noce the sensaons and the feeling                    07. You may consider appreciang each part – say ‘Thank you’ to that part for how it is supporng you.
            08. Slowly and steadily move up the body, scanning up to your head                      09. Once you have scanned up to your head  bring your aenon back to your breathing                       10. Finish the body scan by focusing on the way the whole body is feeling </item>
        <item>1. Get comfortable in your meditaon posion                  2. Relax and focus on your breathing                        3. Bring your awareness to the sounds you hear.                             4. Try and idenfy the sounds and then let it fade away from your consciousness
            5. Slowly bring your focus to the room you are presently in.           What sounds can you hear in the room?                       6. Slowly bring your awareness closer to you, just around your body.                  Become aware of the space, the sound of your breathing, heartbeat.
            8. Stay in the moment for a few seconds and become aware of the sensaons and feelings you are experiencing.                        9. In case your mind wanders, bring the focus back to the breathing
</item>
        <item>01. Get comfortable in your meditaon posion                    02. Relax and focus on your breathing                         03. Slowly, with the next breath bring your awareness to your feet                        04. Noce for the feelings and sensaons                       05. As you concentrate, imagine your feet becoming heavy and secure on the ?oor.
            06. Now as you connue breathing, imagine and feel the long roots coming out of your feet and going deep into the ground.                       08. Stay with the feeling for a while                           09. As you focus on your feet, slowly feel yourself sinking back into your whole body again.
            10. Noce which parts of you are touching the ?oor,                         chair or bed and realize how solid and heavy they feel.                       11. Slowly as you breathe let the image of the growing roots fade away.
            12. Become aware of how di?erently you feel now – You are grounded
 </item>
        <item>01. Get comfortable in your meditaon posion                     02. As you pay aenon to the breathing,                   imagine what is most comforng and cleansing for you                     (warm sunshine or may be a so gentle rain).                     04. Give yourself some me to think create and re?ect about it.
            Strengthen your relaonship with it by making it as vivid as possible.                          06. Connue to breathe as you process the image in your mind                            08. Become aware of how you are feeling.                      Once you feel the image is vivid and powerful, slowly place yourself in it.
            09. Imagine a gentle smile appearing on your face.                       10. Hold on to that feeling of cleansing and comfort.                            11. When you are ready, return to normal breathing and as you do so let the image fade away.                  12. Become aware of how di?erently you feel now –        are you feeling calm and refreshed</item>
        <item>01. Get comfortable in your meditaon posion                  02. Focus on the area where the breathing is more vivid and tangible.                        03. Now imagine an image of the most magni?cent mountain.                       Let it gradually come into greater focus.                       04. Noce how massive it is, how solid, how unmoving, how beauful it is.
            05. When you feel ready,                 bring the mountain into your own body so that your body and the mountain in your mind’s eye become one.                       Resonate with the massiveness,                    sllness and majesty of the mountain.
            06. With each breath, make the image more vivid ll you become a breathing mountain               07. Connue breathing and keep reminding yourself that you are the mountain and start to resonate with its strength and stability              08. Stay with the feeling for some me
            09. When you are ready,               return to normal breathing and as you do so let the image fade away.                10. Become aware of how di?erently you feel now –             are you feeling refreshed and strong</item>
        <item>01.Sit in a comfortable, meditaon posion                       02. Focus on your breathing.                    03. As you concentrate,             think of a di?cult or stressful situaon.               04. Become aware of the emoons and stay with that feeling for some me.                      05. Noce how it is a?ecng your body,
            your breathing and your mental emoonal state.                      06. Now choose to let it go.                       07. Now repeat the same,                   now with something that makes you feel really good.
            Sink into this emoon                           08. Stay with that feeling for some me.                     09. Noce the smile coming back to your face.                  Let it become a big,            generous smile.                Noce the changes you feel inside: physically,  emoonally         and mentally.
            10. Allow the feeling of wellbeing to increase and swell inside and around you.                      11. Enjoy the moment             12. When you are ready,                return to normal breathing                14. Become aware of how di?erently you feel now –               You are posive and happy</item>
        <item>01. Sit in a comfortable, meditaon posture               02. Focus on your breathing.                  Don’t force it let it come and go naturally.              03. As you concentrate,              think of the thoughts that is worrying you and causing anxiety.                    04. Write them virtually in the air.
            05. Now imagine that thought to pass away on a conveyer belt  to a very faraway ‘no man’s’ land.                     06. Do not ?ght, suppress the thoughts that are troubling you.                    07. Simply allow them to come and go. Stay with that feeling for some me.
                             08. Now when you are ready idenfy acvies that you can turn to when you want to switch o? from worrying                09. Crystalize that acvity in your mind and make it vivid.                Now slowly put yourself in that acvity.                    10. Noce the feeling that you are experiencing while doing that acvity.
            Noce how it is a?ecng your body                     11. Now choose to let that also go.                  12. Repeat this exercise                 13. When you are ready open your eyes and become aware of how di?erently you feel now
</item>
        <item>01. Sit comfortably in a meditaon posture                       02. Bring awareness  to your breath                     03. Bring your awareness,                to the image of the individual that disturbed you or caused you hurt                  04. With the next breath consciously say             I forgive you and soen toward that person.
            05. Imagine the person coming into your heart just for now as you breathe in.                           Hold him/her there for a moment,               staying present with that person,                 feeling forgiveness                      06. Now let that person go,                           Be aware of yourself again
            07. Repeat the same  with someone whom you have harmed in some way and mindfully,                  connuing breathing ask for forgiveness.                     Open your heart to this person and imagine him opening his heart to you.                         08. Breathing in, and breathing out,                    slowly let that image fade away
            09. To conclude,                 now, imagine your own image,                      look at yourself and say “I forgive you for whatever you feel you’ve done.                         10. Feel the sensaon of opening your heart to yourself,                            Allow the sensaon of forgiveness to spread between you and your image
            11. Allow this feeling to grow and expand,                     breathing in,                         breathing out,                  relaxing.                      When you are ready open your eyes </item>
        <item>1. Sit comfortably with your back straight and close your eyes                    2. Bring awareness ?rst to the sounds you hear and then to your breath                           3. With your awareness,                      choose a piece of food.              Try something like a nut,                     apple or chocolate
            4. Mindfully look at the food,                         observe and admire the shape,                              colour and texture                       5. Place the food on your tongue and noce how it feels and the response of your salivary glands                     6. Next slowly bite into the food.                           Mindfully chew it nocing the sound, texture and feeling
                        7. Actually take me to noce the sensaon of the food as you swallow the food                  8. Now in your mind say the name of the food,                   acknowledge it and be grateful
</item>
        <item>01. Sit comfortably in a meditaon posture                                 02. Bring awareness ?rst to the sounds you hear and then  to your breath                          03. As you focus on your breathing,                        think about your cravings.                  Recognize it as an urge.                     Do not try to change it or get rid of it.
            04. Use your imaginaon to give the urge a physical form and let it gradually come into greater focus.                       05. Stay with this image for a while and make this image as vivid and strong as possible                        06. With ease slowly loose the ?xaon.                          Imagine it to  dri away from you and fade away to a distance.
            Stay with that moment for some me. 07. Bring focus back to your breathing and as you do so slowly think about all the good intenons and posives about overcoming the urge. 08. Here also give these good intenons a form and imagine in coming towards you, each step making it larger and more vivid. 09. Build in the intensity and stay with that image. Re?ect on how it makes you feel. Slowly start to resonate with that feeling
            10. When you are ready slowly open your eyes and become aware of the moment</item>
        <item>01. Get to a meditaon posture 02.                Focus on your breath.            Don’t force it let it come and go naturally.                  03. As you concentrate,                  think about what makes you smile.                  04. Focus on the image of yourself smiling.                   05. Sink into the emoon associated with that situaon
            08. Stay with that feeling for some me.                 09. Now re?ect upon how you might capture that smile or memory,                a photo,         a painng,        a piece of clothing,           a scent.               10. As you store up these items in your thoughts,               resolve that you will draw them close to you when you ?nish your meditaon or aer you go back home today.
            11. Imagine the item being in a special place close to you and re?ect on how that makes you feel.            13. Are you smiling as you do so?            14. When you are ready,             refocus your thoughts on where you are right now</item>
        <item>cSit in a comfortable, upright posion and close your eyes              02. Focus on your breathing.                Don’t force it let it come and go naturally.                03. Noce for the feelings and sensaons                04. When you are ready open your eyes and acknowledge your partner for this exercise.               05. Invite the partner to speak on the topic of their choice
            06. While the partner is speaking,              you are requested to listen to him/her intently              07. Re?ect on the choice of words,             the emoons that you can feel.                         08. Once the speaker ?nishes,               Share what you have heard                09. Noce what you are saying,                    is it a mere paraphrase?
            What do you feel when you are retelling the story?               How do you feel about the person/partner now                   10. Become aware of these feeling and emoons                 11. Now switch roles and repeat the exercise
</item>
        <item>01. Sit in a comfortable,                  upright posion and close your eyes                02. Focus on your breathing.                03. Noce for the feelings and sensaons                   04. As you concentrate,                   draw up the di?erent tasks that you need to get done today.                   Idenfy each of them                      05. Recognize the urgency that you are feeling to get into acon.
            Stay with that feeling              06. Slowly with the next breath imagine a blank canvas in front of you,                there is also a supply of colours.                 Make this as vivid as possible,                recognize the colours in front of you,                    and imagine the feeling of the brush.                    07. You are now about to paint the most beauful rose.
            08. Resist the urge to get in to acon.                   09. Slowly let the image of the rose come to life.                   Imagine the colour,             the folds of the petals,             the spikes of the thorns,             the feel of the stem                  10. Now with the next breath start to paint the rose part by part,          the stem,        leaves,
            the petals and slowly visualize it come to life                 11. As you do so stay with the painng step by stem and idenfy your emoons that you are experiencing seeing the ?ower come to life.                12. Once your ?ower is ready,                 look at it and resonate with its beauty                13. When you’re ready,                   open your eyes and bring ring your aenon back into the room.
</item>
        <item>01. Sit in a comfortable, upright posion and close your eyes                 02. Focus on your breathing.                    Become aware of the breath going in and out.                     03. Don’t force it let it come and go naturally.                      04. Noce for the feelings and sensaons                   05. As you concentrate,               draw up the di?erent things that are worrying you
            06. Idenfy each one of them and if ok with you give it a form                   07. Then with the next breath label the worry as ‘Just worrying’ and imagine pung into a big bowl.                    Bring the aenon back to the breath and change the subject of their thinking.                 08. Repeat this with all your worries one aer the other and each me.              09. Do this e?ortlessly,
            each me focus on your breath.                10. When you are ready open your eyes and re?ect on the current feeling.
</item>

    </string-array>

</resources>